# Alexey Gronskiy

Zurich, Switzerland +41 79 845 4046 Homepage: gronskiy.com ♂ LinkedIn: agronskiy 대 This CV (up to date): gron.sk/cv ♂



# Summary

Mathematician by training, computer science PhD, with experience in both corporations and startups, I worked in range of roles from software eningeering to data and ML engineering, and in range of fields from computer vision for airborne collision avoidance to financial data analysis. I am a private pilot and paramedic assistant in my free time. In software development, my priorities are systematism and clear communication.

- 5 years industry (Software Engineering)
- Permanent Swiss residence permit ("C")
- o 6 years academia (PhD, Computer Science) o Married, two children

## Skills

Listed below are the skills split into "fresh" and "past" ("secondary") ones. The latter can be brushed up quickly.

### "Fresh"

## Areas of activity

- Machine learning, deep learning
- Computer vision for autonomous flight
- Object detection, collision avoidance
- Simulation and real data fusion
- Large scale data analysis, ETL pipelines
- Neural networks verification and certification
- Code review and documentation process
- Navigating regulatory standards
- MSc/BSc theses advisory

## Operating programming languages

∘ C++ Python o Go

# Software frameworks Tensorflow, Keras

- o gRPC/REST Pandas, Geopandas
- Scikit-learn, PyMC3 Networkx, OSMnx
- o Plotly, Dash, Folium

Flask

- OpenCV
- Stacks & Tools
- o CI/CD: Bazel, Jenkins, Docker, Git, Arcanist
- Packages: Nix, JFrog Artifactory, Anaconda
- Data: Hadoop MapReduce, Spark, Parquet
- o [No]SQL: Redis, MongoDB, MariaDB
- o GCP: Storage, Computing, KubeFlow
- Azure: Databricks & DataLake, DevOps
- o Training: Determined AI, CUDA
- o Organizational: Phabricator, JIRA, Confluence

# "Secondary"

## "Past" and Areas of activity

- Natural Language Processing
- Question reformulation, morphological analysis
- Statistical Learning Theory
- Algorithmic robustness under uncertainty
- Teaching assistance
- External API design for SDK products
- Cross-platform UI development
- Database normalization analysis

### **Programming languages & Software frameworks**

- COM/COM+ o C# WinAPI/MFC o Qt4
- MATLAB
- HTML/JS/CSS Hugo/Jekyll

### Stacks & Tools

- o CI/CD: Google's Blaze, Mercurial, Bazaar, SVN, o Cloud: Google's Borg
- Data: Apache Beam, RabbitMQ
- Databases: MySQL, PostgreSQL

- OpenMP

- various internal code review tools

- o Organizational: UML
- Typesetting: LATEX

# Working Experience

### 2020–2021 Senior data engineer, SIX Banking Services, Zurich, Switzerland



- Organized technical stack, code review and other processes in a newly established data science unit.
  - Performed analytical support of stakeholder business units, provided analysis and computed KPIs for ongoing projects in payment ecosystems.
- $\circ\;$  Participated in preparatory work for transition to cloud pipelines
- o Skills: Python, Geospatial analysis, Mircosoft Azure (Data Factory, DataLake, Databricks), JFrog Artifactory, data security and compliance.

### 2018-2020

# Machine learning & computer vision engineer, Daedalean Al (ddln.ai &), Zurich, Switzerland



- Conceived and developed a prototype of a visual air-to-air object detection and tracking system (as part of autopilot collision avoidance).
- Researched, evaluated and made early technical decisions, shaped out data acquisition and annotation strategies. Developed evaluation metrics, navigated aviation industry standards on operational performance.
- As part of a 4-member team, worked with European Aviation Safety Agency on defining the concepts of safety assurance for neural networks (coauthored gron.sk/codann c, see "Publications").
- Conceived, developed an extendable and modularized machine learning evaluation and reporting
- Co-supervised interns and joint MSc/semester

framework used across several projects.

- Carried out flight tests as a fixed-wing aircraft
- o Skills: C++14, Python, Tensorflow, Git, object detection and tracking, cloud computing and automation (GCP/GKE/KubeFlow/Jenkins), operational performance metrics, technical ownership, requirements design, product development cycle.

# summer 2017 Research intern, Research and Machine Intelligence, Google Zurich, Switzerland



- Worked on answer ranking module for active question reformulation (see Google AI blog post 12).
- Developed several deep learning models for answer ranking.
- Presented at monthly meeting of Google Research.
- Approved for full-time conversion by the hiring committee.
- Skills: Python, C++11, Tensorflow, NLP, experimental design, MapReduce, communication.

# **ETH** zürich

# 2012–2018 **Doctoral research assistant, head teaching assistant**, Machine Learning Group, Department of Computer Science, ETH Zurich, Switzerland

- o Conducted research in both theoretical and practical fields (see "Projects" below).
- o Launched medical collaborations with University Hospital Zurich (see www.cardioml.ch ぱ).
- Supervised several MSc theses.
- o Taught "Introduction to Machine Learning" and "Statistical Learning Theory" courses, created a script for the latter.

## 2010–2012 C++ software engineer, ABBYY Software, Moscow, Russia

- Worked on a framework for automated native language understanding and translation.
- Designed, developed SDK wrappers for language
- morphology analysis and text classification.
- Skills: C++03, C#, COM/COM+/WinAPI, SVN, interface design, internal libraries, UML.

## 2008–2011 Independent (freelance) C++ developer

- Conceived and developed a cross-platform (Mac/Linux/Windows) tool for photo management, sold and maintained it.
- Skills: C++03, Qt 4, MercurialHg, PostgreSQL, selling and presentation.

# Research Projects, Working Groups, Publications and Talks

### Working Group





- Participated in a working group (gron.sk/easa ♂) Co-authored a report "Concepts of Design Assurwhich aimed at establishing methods and concepts for ensuring operational safety of machine learning models in aviation.
  - ance for Neural Networks", whose official summary (gron.sk/codann ♂) was published by EASA.

Research Projects Statistical Mechanical Analysis of Combinatorial Free Energy, ETH Zurich with Center of & Publications Science of Information, Purdue University



PURDUE

- - International Conference on Analysis of Algorithms (AofA) 2017, Princeton
  - tion Problems"
    - Analytic Combinatorics (SODA-ANALCO) 2017, Barcelona
- o "On Phase Transitions of Free Energy in Combi- o "Free Energy Rates for a Class of Optimization Problems"
  - International Conference on Analysis of Algorithms (AofA) 2014, Paris
  - "Phase Transitions in Parameter Rich Optimiza- o "Asymptotic Evaluation of Posterior Agreement for some Optimization Problems" J. of Theor. Comp. Sci. (TCS) 2018

- o "On Informativeness and Robustness of Algo- o "How Informative are Minimum Spanning Tree rithms"
  - Joint ETH & Google Workshop, Google, Zurich, 2016
- Algorithms"
  - International Symposium on Information Theory (ISIT) 2014, Hawaii



Machine Learning for Cardiological Diseases (www.cardioml.ch ☑), ETH Zurich with University Hospital Zurich and MPI Tübingen, Germany

Robustness and Informativeness of Minimum Spanning Tree Algorithm, ETH Zurich



- tween key factors of Acute Coronary and Takotsubo syndromes.
- Detecting causal and statistical dependencies be Launched and co-led the project initially, supervised BSc and MSc theses.

## Robust Solving of Algorithmic Problems, ETH Zurich with Institute of Theoretical Informatics, 7urich

o "Robust Optimization in the Presence of Uncertainty: a Generic Approach" J. of Computer and System Sciences (JCSS) 2018

# Education

# **ETH** zürich

2012–2018 Doctoral degree (Dr. Sci. ETH), Machine Learning Group, Department of Computer Science, ETH Zurich, Switzerland

> o Ph.D. Thesis "Statistical Mechanics and Information Theory for Approximate Robust Inference" (gron.sk/thesis ♂).



2006–2011 BSc + MSc, Department of Mathematics and Mechanics, Chair of Discrete Mathematics, Moscow State University of M.V. Lomonosov (MSU), Russia

- Specialist (equiv. BSc + MSc) degree in Pure and Applied Mathematics, with Honors.
- Thesis "On some metrical properties of Boolean functions" (gron.sk/msc-thesis \(\mathcal{C}\)).

# Languages

 Russian . . . . . . . . . . native o German . . . . fluent (C2 Goethe, 2016) o English..... fluent French . . . . . . fluent (C1 DALF, 2011)

## Volunteer Work

2014-curr. Ambulance assistant (Emergency Medical Technician, EMT), Zurich Fire & Rescue Service, Switzerland



- Regularly training as an ambulance assistant.
- Participating in ambulance shifts during public events in the city of Zurich.
- o First responder to alarms from large-scale emergencies.

2007–2012 Lecturer/Teacher, MSU-/MIPT-based summer and winter schools of for mathematics and programming, Russia



- Created original lecture/seminar materials.
- Conducted lectures and seminars for high school students.
- o Topics: mathematical analysis, discrete mathematics, programming.

# Hobbies and Other Activities

Aviation Pilot, SWISS Flying Club (www.swissflyingclub.ch 2), Hausen am Albis, Switzerland



- Private Pilot License (PPL(A)), single engine piston (SEP) class rating. SWISS Flying Club • 120+ hours flight time.
- contests
- Programming o II prize team, All-Russia Programming Contest II prize team, Moscow Programming Contest (2005).
  - (2005).

- Sports & Music O Karate (gold medal in Swiss Spring Kyu- O Alpine skiing and snowboarding. tournament, 2014).

  - o Playing flute, guitar.

Pilot blog Author, Telegram channel "CrossWind Landing" (in Russian) (gron.sk/x-wind 다)



- o Telling the story of learning for private pilot license in Switzerland. o Topics about aerodynamics, meteorology, and the fun of flying.
- Blog **Author**, Personal blog on range of topics (gron.sk/posts ♂)
  - o Topics: aviation, tech, programming.